Register of the Franklin Lindsay papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Franklin Lindsay papers
1944-1998
46034
Hoover Institution Archives
17 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (7.2 linear feet)
Reports, memoranda, correspondence, and photocopies of Office of Strategic Services and British government documents relating to resistance movements in Yugoslavia during World War II, Allied relations with them, Office of Strategic Services operations in Yugoslavia and Austria, post-World War II economic recontruction in western Europe, the Organization for European Economic Cooperation, and American foreign aid to Europe. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Lindsay, Franklin, 1916-
Access
Collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1946, with increments received in 1982, 1992, 1993 and 2010.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1916 March 12 Born in Kenton, Ohio
1938 A.B., Stanford University
1938-1939 With Columbia Division, U.S. Steel Corp.
1940-1945 Served in the Army of the United States, to Lieutenant Colonel
1944-1945 With the Office of Strategic Services
1945 Chief, American Military Mission to Yugoslavia
1946 Executive assistant to Bernard Baruch, U.S. Delegation, U.N. Atomic Energy Commission
1947-1948 Consultant, House Select Committee on Foreign Aid (Herter Committee)
1948-1949 Served as an American representative to the Organization for European Economic Co-operation, Paris
1949-1953 With the Central Intelligence Agency
1953-1956 With the Public Affairs Program, Ford Foundation
1954 Consultant, Second Hoover Commission
1956-1961 With McKinsey & Co., Inc.
1961-1962 Executive Vice President, Itek Corp.
1962-1975 President, Itek Corp.
1975- Chairman of the Board, Itek Corp.
Scope and Content of Collection
Reports, memoranda, correspondence, and photocopies of Office of Strategic Services and British government documents relating to resistance movements in Yugoslavia during World War II, Allied relations with them, Office of Strategic Services operations in Yugoslavia and Austria, post-World War II economic recontruction in western Europe, the Organization for European Economic Cooperation, and American foreign aid to Europe.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Organisation for European Economic Co-operation.; United States. Office of Strategic Services.; Austria.; Economic assistance, American.; Europe.; Great Britain.; Reconstruction (1939-1951)--Europe.; Secret service--United States.; United States--Armed Forces.; United States--Foreign relations.; World War, 1939-1945--Austria.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; World War, 1939-1945--Secret service.; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.; World War, 1939-1945--Yugoslavia.; World War, 1939-1945.; Yugoslavia--History--Axis occupation, 1941-1945.; Yugoslavia.
- European Recovery Program, 1947-1948 (Box 1-7)
  Scope and Contents note
  Printed, mimeographed, hectographed, typescript, holographic, and handwritten reports; memoranda; and correspondence relating to the Interim Report on the European Recovery Programme drafted by the Organization for European Economic Co-operation in 1948 and to its annual programs, arranged as listed.
  - General (Box 1)
    - "Capital Investment and Production Coordination," memorandum from Foster to Richard M. Bissell, 1948 July 6; Two typescript drafts (carbon copies).
    - "Comments on Problems Raised by the First Draft of the Mechanism of Foreign Relief and Reconstruction," memorandum from W. Y. Elliott to Allen W. Dulles, 1948 October 18; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 1)
    - "Draft Executive Committee Resolution Concerning O.E.E.C. Relations with the Press," memorandum, 1948 August 2; Mimeographed copy. (Box 1)
    - "Draft Note from the Secretary General to the Council on Relations between O.E.E.C. and the United States Special Representative in Europe," memorandum., 1948 June 27; Mimeographed copy. (Box 1)
    - "Draft Report of the Committee of Financial Experts on the Examination of the Mutual Aid Plan During the Period of the Marshall Plan," memorandum, 1948 May; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 1)
    - "ECA Observers of OEEC Committees,", undated; Mimeographed lists. (Box 1)
    - "Hoffman's 34 Basic Functions of ECA," memorandum, 1948 July 16; Hectographed copy. (Box 1)
    - "Memorandum on the Preliminary Draft Arrangement for Mutual Assistance Between Participating Countries During the Period Covered by the European Rehabilitation Programme,", 1948 May 24; Mimeographed copy. (Box 1)
    - "Report of Committee (Advisory Steering Committee) on Organization for ERP," State Department memorandum by Melvin L. Manfull, 1947 October 21; Hectographic copy. (Box 1)
    - "Selective Topical Index of P.L. 472, Title I," index for the Economic Cooperation Act of 1948, undated; Mimeographed copy. (Box 1)
    - Miscellany (Box 1)
  - Organization for European Economic Co-operation (Box 1)
    - Council, minutes of meetings, 1948; Mimeographed copies. (Box 1)
      - May 12-August 4 (Box 1)
      - August 5-September 11 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee, minutes of meetings, 1948 September 20-October 14; Mimeographed copies. (Box 1)
    - Intra-European Trade and Payments (Box 1)
      - Official memoranda (Box 1)
        - 1948 June-August (Box 1)
        - 1948 October-November (Box 1)
      - Reports (Box 1)
        - "Agreement for Intra-European Payments and Compensations: Report for October," by the Bank for International Settlements, 1948 November 23; Mimeographed copy. (Box 1)
        - "Application of the Intra-European Payments Scheme," by A. W. Marget, memorandum, 1948 October 12; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 1)
        - "Balance of Payments Information," memorandum from A. W. Marget to C. Hoover, 1948 July 28; Typescript. (Box 1)
        - "Comparison of 26 May Paper with Present Situation," by Lindsay, memorandum, 1948 August 1 (?); Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 1)
        - "Creation of Additional National Currency Counterpart to Facilitate Intra-European Payments," memorandum from W. M. Tomlinson to A. W. Marget, 1948 June 11; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 1)
        - "Estimates of Intra-ERP Dollar Payments in the Third Quarter," memorandum from Richard M. Bissell to W. A. Harriman, 1948 July 2; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 1)
        - "The External Aspects of Europe's Economic Problems," by E. A. G. Robinson and G. D. A. MacDougall, memorandum, undated; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 1)
        - "Intra-European Balances of Payments," memorandum from Geiger and Lindsay to Bissell, 1948 April 30; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 1)
        - "The Intra-European Clearing System," by Geiger and Lindsay, memorandum, 1948 May 24; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 1)
        - "Intra-European Payments Clearing System," memorandum, 1948 May 27; Typescript (carbon and photocopies). (Box 1)
        - "Intra-European Trade and Payments: Basic Document," report, undated; Mimeographed copy. (Box 1)
        - "Intra-European Trade Payments Problem," memorandum from the National Advisory Council, 1948 June 2; Mimeographed copy and cover letter. (Box 1)
        - "Introduction of Incentives into the Multilateral Payments Scheme," memorandum from Lindsay to C. Hoover, 1948 September 4; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 1)
        - Letter from Hammarskjold to Rosen, 1948 September 6; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 1)
        - Letter from W. Averell Harriman to R. Marjolin, 1948 June 14; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 1)
        - Letter from R. Marjolin to W. Averell Harriman, 1948 June 9; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 1)
        - "Memorandum on Some Aspects of Intra-European Trade and Payments," memorandum from G. Malagodi, 1948 May 10; Two typescripts (carbon copies). (Box 1)
        - "Methods of Allocating Conversion of $70m Among Creditor Countries," memorandum, 1948 May 25; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 1)
        - "Multilateralization of European Payments," reports prepared by the Research Department of the International Monetary Fund, 1947-1948; Mimeographed copy and cover letter. (Box 2)
        - "Notes on Conversation with Gerald Van Loo of the U.K. Treasury on the Intra-European Payments Scheme," by Lindsay, memorandum, 1948 September 23; Typescript. (Box 2)
        - "Observations on Post-War Pattern of Intra-European Trade," by Tomlinson (?), memorandum, 1948 May; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 2)
        - "OEEC Allocations and the Intra-European Payments Proposal,", 1948 September 2; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 2)
        - "Offshore Procurement in Europe," by Lindsay, memorandum, 1948 May 12; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 2)
        - "Outline of an Integrated Plan for the Financing and Multilateralization of Intra-European Payments," memorandum, undated; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 2)
        - "Outline of Intra-European Payments Problem and Suggested Solution," by Tomlinson (?), memorandum, 1948 May; Typescript. (Box 2)
        - "Progress of Finance Working Party on Intra-European Payments," memorandum by Tomlinson to Marget, 1948 June; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 2)
        - "A Proposal for the Revival of Intra-European Trade on a Miltilateral Basis," memorandum from Th. Geiger to W. Y. Elliott, 1947 September 29; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 2)
        - "Proposal for Use of E.R.P. Funds in Conjunction with Credit for Loosening Up Intra-European Payments Position," by Connally, memorandum, 1948 May; Typescript. (Box 2)
        - "Recent Progress of OEEC on Intra-European Trade and Payments," memorandum by William M. Tomlinson to W. Averell Harriman, 1948 June 7; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 2)
        - "Recommended Measures to Reduce Demand on U.S. During Third Quarter by Promoting Trade in European Exportable Surpluses," memorandum from Paul R. Porter to W. Averell Harriman, 1948 June 10; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 2)
        - "Schema d'assistence mutuelle," memorandum from F. le Norcy to W. Tomlinson, 1948 May 10; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 2)
        - "Western Hemisphere Payments," memorandum from Finletter to Lindsay, undated; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 2)
        - Miscellany (Box 2)
    - Programs (Box 2)
      - Program for the fourth quarter, memoranda, 1948; Mimeographed and typescript copies. (Box 2)
      - Program for "Report to ECA on the First Annual Programme, 1st July 1948 to 30th July 1949,", 1948-1949; Mimeographed copies. (Box 2)
        - Part I, General (Box 2)
        - Part II, Reports to Technical Committees (Box 2)
        - Amendments (Box 2)
        - Export-import tables by country (Box 2)
        - Export-import tables by commodity (Box 2)
        - Press communique (Box 2)
        - Part I, in French (Box 3)
        - Part II, in French (Box 3)
      - Program for 1949-50 (Box 3)
        - General, memoranda, Mimeographed copies. (Box 3)
        - "OSR (Office of the Special Representative) Comments on OEEC Interim Report," memorandum, undated; Mimeographed copy. (Box 3)
        - "Review of OEEC Report on the 1949/50 Program," memorandum by Carter de Paul and Phyllis Leuchtenburg to Bob Macy, undated; Mimeographed copy. (Box 3)
      - Long term program (1949-52) (Box 3)
        - General, memoranda, Mimeographed copies. (Box 3)
        - Preparation of the reports (Box 3)
          - Timetables for preparation of the Interim Report, memoranda, Mimeographed and typescript copies. (Box 3)
          - Instructions for preparation of national programs, memoranda, Mimeographed copies. (Box 3)
          - Screening of national programs, memoranda, Mimeographed copies. (Box 3)
          - Progress reports, memoranda, Mimeographed, typescript, and handwritten copies. (Box 3)
          - "Statistical Summary of the National Long Term Programmes," memorandum, 1948 November 10; Mimeographed copy. (Box 3)
          - "Technical Aspects of the Long Term Programme," memorandum, 1948 November 25; Mimeographed copy and cover letter. (Box 3)
        - Reports on programming activities (Box 3)
          - "Draft Note on the Co-ordination of Capital Development Programmes," memorandum, undated; Two typescripts (carbon copies). (Box 3)
          - "General Outline for Statistical Indicators of Recovery in the Western European Participating Countries," memorandum to C. Hoover and Arthur from E. R. Gray, 1948 September 6; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 3)
          - "Measure of Co-operation," draft of unidentified chapter, undated; Typescript and mimeographed copies. (Box 3)
          - "Problems of Collecting, Evaluating and Transmitting ERP Data," by Lindsay and Geiger, 1948 May 24; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 3)
          - "Programming," by Lindsay and Geiger, two drafts of memorandum, 1948 April 30; Typescript (carbon copies). (Box 3)
          - "Report to Washington on the Long Term Program," by Henry B. Arthur, 1948 November 8; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 3)
  - Interim Report on the European Recovery Programme (Box 3)
    - Volume I: "Report of the Council of the Organization for European Economic Co-operation to the United States Economic Co-operation Administrtion, on the First Stages of the European Recovery Programme, dated 30th December 1948," drafts, Mimeographed copies. (Box 3)
      - Table of Contents (Box 3)
        - Draft, 1948 December 11 (Box 3)
        - Draft, 1948 December 21 (Box 3)
      - Tables, miscellaneous charts, Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 3)
      - Chapter 1, "Introduction" (Box 3)
        - Draft, 1948 December 11 (Box 3)
        - Draft, 1948 December 21 (Box 3)
      - Chapter 2, "The Background of Western Europe's Economic Problems" (Box 3)
        - Draft, 1948 December 14 (Box 3)
      - Chapter 3, "The Problems of Production" (Box 3)
        - Draft, 1948 December 12 (Box 3)
        - Draft, 1948 December 18 (Box 3)
      - Chapter 4, "The Balances of Payments with the Outside World" (Box 3)
        - Draft, 1948 December 3 (Box 3)
        - Draft, 1948 December 12 (Box 3)
        - Amendment, 1948 December 12 (Box 4)
        - Draft, 1948 December 21 (Box 4)
      - Chapter 5, "Intra-European Trade and Payments" (Box 4)
        - Draft, 1948 December 14 (Box 4)
        - Draft, 1948 December 21 (Box 4)
      - Chapter 6, "Use of Resources in Western Europe" (Box 4)
        - Draft, 1948 December 12 (Box 4)
        - Draft, 1948 December 21 (Box 4)
      - Chapter 7, "The Role of European Co-operation in the Recovery Programme" (Box 4)
        - Draft, 1948 December 14 (Box 4)
        - Draft, 1948 December 20 (Box 4)
      - Chapter 8, "The Problems Confronting Western Europe" (Box 4)
        - Draft, 1948 December 14 (Box 4)
        - Draft, 1948 December 22 (Box 4)
      - Appendix A, "Summaries of National Programmes" (Box 4)
        - Drafts, 1948 December 11-13 (Box 4)
        - Draft, 1948 December 17 (Box 4)
      - Appendix B, "The Agenda for Future Action," unpublished (Box 4)
        - Draft, 1948 December 13 (Box 4)
      - Amendments, 1948 December 30 (Box 4)
    - Volume II: "National Programmes of Members for the Recovery Period ending 30th June, 1952, Submitted to the Organisation for European Economic Co-operation," drafts and reports, Mimeographed copies. (Box 4)
      - Chapter 1, "Austria" (Box 4)
        - Long term program (Box 4)
        - Discussion of the Long Term Working Group (Box 4)
        - Technical Committee reports (Box 4)
        - Production and consumption tables (Box 4)
        - Memorandum (Box 4)
      - Chapter 2, "Benelux" (Box 4)
        - Long term program (Box 4)
        - Comments by the Secretariat General (Box 4)
        - Production and consumption tables (Box 4)
        - Memoranda (Box 4)
      - Chapter 3, "Denmark" (Box 4)
        - Long term program, Printed copy. (Box 4)
        - Discussion of the Long Term Working Group (Box 4)
        - Technical Committee reports (Box 4)
        - Production and consumption tables (Box 4)
        - Memoranda (Box 4)
      - Chapter 4, "France" (Box 5)
        - Long term program, in French, Printed copy. (Box 5)
        - Discussion of the Long Term Working Group (Box 5)
        - Technical Committee reports (Box 5)
        - Comments by the Secretariat General (Box 5)
        - Production and consumption tables (Box 5)
      - Chapter 5, "Greece" (Box 5)
        - Comments by the Secretariat General (Box 5)
        - Recommended ECA allocations for Greece (Box 5)
        - Balance of payments (Box 5)
        - Memorandum, Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 5)
      - Chapter 6, "Iceland" (Box 5)
        - Technical Committee reports (Box 5)
        - Comments by the Secretariat General and production and consumption tables (Box 5)
        - Balance of payments (Box 5)
      - Chapter 7, "Ireland" (Box 5)
        - Technical Committee reports (Box 5)
        - Comments by the Secretariat General and production and consumption tables (Box 5)
      - Chapter 8, "Italy" (Box 5)
        - Long term program, in French, Printed copy. (Box 5)
        - Discussion of the Long Term Working Group (Box 5)
        - Technical Committee reports (Box 5)
        - Comments by the Secretariat General (Box 5)
        - Production and consumption tables (Box 5)
        - Balance of payments (Box 5)
      - Chapter 9, "Norway" (Box 5)
        - Long term program (Box 5)
        - Discussion of the Long Term Working Group (Box 5)
        - Technical Committee reports (Box 5)
        - Comments by the Secretariat General and production and consumption tables (Box 5)
        - Balance of payments (Box 5)
      - Chapter 10, "Portugal" (Box 6)
        - Long term program (Box 6)
        - Discussion of the Long Term Working Group (Box 6)
        - Technical Committee reports (Box 6)
        - Comments by the Secretariat General (Box 6)
      - Chapter 11, "Sweden" (Box 6)
        - Long term program (Box 6)
        - Discussion of the Long Term Working Group (Box 6)
        - Technical Committee reports (Box 6)
        - Comments by the Secretariat General (Box 6)
        - Production and consumption tables, in French (Box 6)
      - Chapter 12, "Switzerland" (Box 6)
        - Long term program (Box 6)
        - Discussion of the Long Term Working Group (Box 6)
        - Comments by the Secretariat General and production and consumption tables (Box 6)
      - Chapter 13, "Turkey" (Box 6)
        - Discussion of the Long Term Working Group (Box 6)
        - Comments by the Secretariat General and production and consumption tables (Box 6)
      - Chapter 14, "United Kingdom" (Box 6)
        - Long term program, Printed copy. (Box 6)
        - Discussion of the Long Term Working Group (Box 6)
        - Technical committee reports (Box 6)
        - Comments by the Secretariat General and production and consumption tables (Box 6)
        - Memoranda (Box 6)
      - Chapter 15, "Bizone" (Box 6)
        - Long term program (Box 6)
        - Technical Committee reports (Box 6)
        - Comments by the Secretariat General (Box 6)
        - Production and consumption tables (Box 6)
        - Balance of payments (Box 6)
        - Coal report (Box 6)
        - Food and agriculture report (Box 6)
      - Chapter 16, "Bizone" (Box 7)
        - Fuel and power report (Box 7)
        - Industry report (Box 7)
        - Petroleum report (Box 7)
        - Power supply report (Box 7)
        - Trade report (Box 7)
      - Chapter 17, "Trieste" (Box 7)
        - Long term program (Box 7)
        - Discussion of the Long Term Working Group (Box 7)
        - Comments by the Secretariat General and production and consumption tables (Box 7)
    - Volume III: "O.E.E.C. Technical Reports," progress reports, Mimeographed copies. (Box 7)
      - Directives to Technical Committees, 1948 (Box 7)
      - Chemical Products Committee, 1948 November 9 (Box 7)
      - Electricity Committee, 1948 November 5 (Box 7)
      - Food and Agriculture Committee, 1948 November 8 (Box 7)
      - Inland Transport Committee, 1948 November 5 (Box 7)
      - Iron and Steel Committee, 1948 December 3 and 6 (Box 7)
      - Machinery Committee, 1948 November 6 and 24 (Box 7)
      - Manpower Committee, 1948 October 28 and November 6 (Box 7)
      - Maritime Transport Committee, 1948 November 6 (Box 7)
      - Oil Committee, 1948 November 6 (Box 7)
      - Overseas Territories Committee, in French, 1948 November 12 and 17 (Box 7)
      - Raw Materials Committee, 1948 September 27 and November 9 (Box 7)
      - Textiles Committee, 1948 November 6 (Box 7)
      - Timber Committee, 1948 November 6 (Box 7)
      - Tourism Committee, 1948 October 29 (Box 7)
      - Trade Committee, 1948 November 6 (Box 7)
- Subject File, 1944-1958, 1976 (Box 8-9)
  Printed, mimeographed, hectographed, typescript, holographic, and handwritten reports; memoranda; and correspondence relating to the work of the American Mission for Aid to Greece, the Herter Committee, partisan activity in Yugoslavia, and general economic reconstruction in Europe, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - American Mission for Aid to Greece (AMAG) (Box 8)
    - "Additional Information requested by Subcommittee D of the Select Committee on Foreign Aid," report, October 13, 1947.; Mimeographed copy and cover letter. (Box 8)
    - "Agricultural Institutions in Greece," by the Foreign Economic Administration, report, 1944 July; Mimeographed copy. (Box 8)
    - "AMAG Comments on Greek Marshall Aid Plan," report, 1947 November 13; Typescript and cover letter. (Box 8)
    - "Brief Summary of Activities of the Royal Hellenic Navy and U.S. Navy Group's Aid Program," memorandum, 1947 August 12; Mimeographed copy. (Box 8)
    - "Briefing Conference for Jenkins Subcommittee at Embassy," report, 1947 October 6; Typescript (carbon copy) and cover letter. (Box 8)
    - "Comments made by Colonel Lehner before Congressional Group," memorandum, 1947 September 22; Typescript and carbon copy. (Box 8)
    - "Division of Agriculture,", 1947 September 19; Typescript and carbon copy. (Box 8)
    - "Greek Armed Forces." by Pipinelis, memorandum, December 16; "Greek Situation," by Lindsay, memorandum, October 13, 1947; Typescript (carbon copy) and cover letter; typescript (carbon copy). (Box 8)
    - "Information Available Subsequent to the Quarterly Report to Congress," memorandum, undated; Typescript. (Box 8)
    - "Legal Relations between the Mission and the Greek Government," memorandum, undated; Two typescripts (carbon copies). (Box 8)
    - "Memorandum," by M. W. Fodor, 1947 May 27; Typescript. (Box 8)
    - "Northern Provinces of Greece," by Vassili Dendramis, memorandum, 1948 January 8; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 8)
    - "Notes on Reconstruction for Briefing Sessions with Congressional Committees,", undated; Two typescripts (carbon copies). (Box 8)
    - "Opening Statement by Chief of Mission for Congressional Delegation," draft of speech, undated; Two typescripts (carbon copies). (Box 8)